<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-02-13T14:22:39+00:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ahead of the Board Game</title><subtitle>The fun of getting into board games</subtitle><author><name>4binary1</name></author><entry><title type="html">Push-Your-Luck Games: learning when to stop!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Push-Your-Luck_games.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Push-Your-Luck Games: learning when to stop!" /><published>2021-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Push-Your-Luck_games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Push-Your-Luck_games.html">&lt;p&gt;Randomness is a source of uncertainty and uncertainty can result in a spectrum of responses. When this uncertainty is confined within the boundaries of a game it can lead to anxiety but also, and I would object more so, to elation and interest from the player. We could, and will, spend an entire post on the role of randomness in board games but in this one I’d like to focus on one particular way of approaching and implementing randomness in a game: the &lt;em&gt;push-your-luck&lt;/em&gt; mechanic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Push-your-luck or &lt;em&gt;press-your-luck&lt;/em&gt; is an expression used to describe the risk of losing what you already achieved in order to obtain a better result. Based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgamemechanic/2661/push-your-luck&quot;&gt;BGG’s definition&lt;/a&gt;, in push-your-luck games “players must decide between settling for existing gains, or risking them all for further rewards”.&lt;br /&gt;
Many gambling games rely on this mechanic: &lt;em&gt;Blackjack&lt;/em&gt; for instance relies on the single decision from the players to stop or keep going, each time risking more and more. Even TV games use this and one in particular is worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Press Your Luck”&lt;/em&gt; was an American TV game show running in the 80’s which is still remembered today because of the episode where a contestant, Michael Larson, completely broke the game. In the show, players had to answer trivia questions in order to get the chance to play on a board containing a set of prizes that flashed randomly. By pressing a button the flashing would stop and the contestant would add the content of the selectd square to their winning. In a future article we will also discuss how poorly random the randomness we usually deal with is, but this is a splendid example of it: Larson figured out that the flashing had a complex but repetitive pattern and was able to amass a huge amount of winnings in what seemed to be cheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it doesn’t have a lot to do with board games, I find this story really fascinating as it highlights how for a push your luck game to work, it must be balanced so that the players can’t only rely on strategy or knowledge but have to add a bit of gut feeling. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ultimateclassicrock.com/michael-larson-press-your-luck/&quot;&gt;This fun article&lt;/a&gt; covers the “Press Your Luck” scandal in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to board and card games, I mentioned gambling games as often using this mechanic, sometimes exclusively. These games are very popular, successful and often very addictive so the mechaninc could certainly be deemed very fertile for board game designs but that’s not as easy as it seems. One of the most important components of gambling is its relying on real assets, tipically money. The prospect of using a form of entertainment such as games or sport to make a profit is extremely attractive and a lot of gambling games break removing this component. A game like &lt;em&gt;Poker&lt;/em&gt; is much less entertaining when playing for nothing, while even introducing a very small prize gives it meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So making a board game that relies on the push-your-luck mechanic without relying on real assets is definitely a nice design challenge and in the next section I’d like to highlights some games that, in my opinion, achieve that very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/biblios.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Biblios, Steve Finn&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Biblios, Steve Finn&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pure-push-your-luck-games&quot;&gt;Pure push-your-luck games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/41/cant-stop&quot;&gt;Can’t Stop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the oldest game I’ll mention in this post. Designed by Sid Sackson and published for the first time in 1980, this game sees players rolling dice to advance their pawns on tracks associated to the numbers you can obtain with two dice (i.e. from 2 to 12). The higher the chance for a given result, the longer the track is (e.g. the 7 track is longer than the 4 track) and the players can keep rolling as long as they want. However, if they find themselves in a position where no pawn can be advances, they bust out and lose all progress made that turn. If they stop they can instead “save” their progress and start from a better position next round. This game is a classic that gets all players around the table shouting for whoever is playing to stop or to bust out. A great implementation for &lt;em&gt;Can’t Stop&lt;/em&gt; is available for free on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.boardgamearena.com/gamepanel?game=cantstop&quot;&gt;Board Game Arena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/265256/push&quot;&gt;PUSH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was designed by the game design studio called Prospero Hall which in recent years has delivered some truly well designed games. &lt;em&gt;PUSH&lt;/em&gt; is no different and represents a simple and clean implementation of the push-your-luck mechanic. In the game, players draw cards and sort them in up to three piles following a simple rule: colors and numbers can’t repeat in a pile. It’s up to them to decide wether to stop and collect the best pile or keep drawing to collect an higher score. If they are too greedy they might have to bust out and roll a die which will cause them to lose everything they’ve collected of a given colour. This game layers the mechanic in a pretty interesting way: you can be greedy with your draws and still get away with a lucky roll of the die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/169654/deep-sea-adventure&quot;&gt;Deep Sea Adventure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; from Jun Sasaki and Goro Sasaki belongs to a collection of games published in japan by Oink Games that fit in a very small box. In the game, players are deep sea divers trying to collect treasure from the depths of the ocean. Each turn they can decide to swim deeper to collect richer treasure or come back up to the submarine. In the latter case they get to keep the treasure they collected while if they keep going they risk running out of air and losing everything they got. This is another simple and very fun implementation of the mechanic and one that fits in a super small package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/coloretto.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloretto, Michael Schacht&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Coloretto, Michael Schacht&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blurring-the-lines&quot;&gt;Blurring the lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the push-your-luck mechanic can stand on its own to make a fairly interesting game, the idea is often included in more complicated rule sets to add an element of risk and variety. This is the case for the following games which adopt the mechanic without making it the centerpiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/5782/coloretto&quot;&gt;Coloretto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, from designer Michael Schacht, is definitely the closest to pure push-your-luck in this short list. This is one of those small box treasures that everyone should have in their collection. The game mixes the mechanic with set collection in an addicting experience. Here players draw cards from a deck and divide them in heaps (similar to what happens in &lt;em&gt;PUSH&lt;/em&gt;). Alternatively they can collect one of the heaps to add colored chameleons to their collection. They have to be careful though, as only three colors will score them points at the end, while all additional colors will cost them points instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/244521/quacks-quedlinburg&quot;&gt;The Quacks of Quedlinburg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is one of the great games from a designer I’ve come to love recently: Wolfgang Warsch. Here players participate in a competition where they are asked to prepare the best potion. By drawing chits from a bag they will move along a track that will score them points and let them earn coins they can spend to improve their bag. The mix of push-your-luck and bag building is exquisite and moves extremely fast thanks to simultaneous turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/34219/biblios&quot;&gt;Biblios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was designed by Steve Finn and is a very peculiar game. The medieval theme of abbots might push people away but the game packs super juicy decisions in two simple phases. In the first phase you will acquire cards while at the same time leaving some for your opponents. This is where the push-your-luck comes into play. The second round players will then auction the rest of the deck with the goal of collecting the most cards for one or more of the 5 available colors. &lt;em&gt;Biblios&lt;/em&gt; is a game that always surprises people when they see what tough choices a small brown box can put them in front of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/quacks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quacks of Quedlinburg, Wolfgang Warsch&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Quacks of Quedlinburg, Wolfgang Warsch&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fun-in-push-your-luck-games&quot;&gt;The fun in push-your-luck games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are, pun intended, that you have played and enjoyed a push-your-luck game already. Wether it was a gambling game to be played with the family over the holidays, or a board game that challenges you to “roll one more time”. If that’s the case then you already experiences what makes such mechanic fun to play. And in the unlikely case you never have: I urge you to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rush of pushing for one more round and the satisfaction of getting a better result because you dared make the whole experience adventurous, regardless of the theme. Moreover, boardgames have, in my opinion, an edge over classic gambling games when it comes to loss. While winning money or something concrete feels definitely better than winning bragging rights over your friends, losing a real asset is much worse than losing a game. Indeed, the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loss_aversion&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;loss aversion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; suggests that we fear losing a given amount of something much more than we enjoy gaining the same amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sense, board games that use push-your-luck allow players to experience the positive  feeling of making a “right” call and even encourage them to be “pushier” than they normally would as the stakes are lower. So next time you can, take the chance on a push-your-luck game, you might get an unexpected favorable outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">Randomness is a source of uncertainty and uncertainty can result in a spectrum of responses. When this uncertainty is confined within the boundaries of a game it can lead to anxiety but also, and I would object more so, to elation and interest from the player. We could, and will, spend an entire post on the role of randomness in board games but in this one I’d like to focus on one particular way of approaching and implementing randomness in a game: the push-your-luck mechanic.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/coloretto-header.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Party Games: strength in numbers!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Party-Games.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Party Games: strength in numbers!" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Party-Games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Party-Games.html">&lt;p&gt;Parties: 2020 hasn’t seen a lot of those. At the time I’m writing this post party is an almost obsolete word that mostly applies to looking at people’s heads through a screen. But social gatherings were, are and will be extremely important. So it shouldn’t come as a surprise that a very successful category of the board gaming hobby is represented by &lt;em&gt;Party Games&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Party games are games that encourage social interaction. They generally have easy setups and simple rules, and they can accommodate large groups of people and play in a short amount of time” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgamecategory/1030/party-game&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
I think this definition perfectly sums up what I would consider a party game, although each of the three pillars is pretty malleable. The Victorian era has contributed a lot to the popularization of group games played indoors. These are called &lt;em&gt;parlour games&lt;/em&gt;, due to the location where the British upper classes would play them, and a classic example is &lt;em&gt;Charades.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays the market is flooded with party games, due to their accessibility and tipically reduced cost. In order to navigate modern party games I like to divide them into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social deduction games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suggestion games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, this separation is not part of the common board game lingo although, for instance, social deduction games represent a well defined category. Processing party games through these lenses, helps me understand the kind of experience that they want to create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/pictomania.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pictomania, Vlaada Chvátil&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Pictomania, Vlaada Chvátil&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;team-games&quot;&gt;Team games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name suggests, in team games players are divided into two or more groups that compete for victory. The most successful games that I can think of within this category are word games. These have gained a lot of traction in recent years probably due to the very reduced rulesets and the extremely clever design of the most famous examples. Three games, in my opinion, perfectly represent this category for modern board games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/178900/codenames&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Codenames&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a game by Vlaada Chvátil that has become so popular in recent years that it has seen a plethora of re-implementations with different themes. In the game, a player from each team tries to hint words to their teammates by using only one word and one number, suggesting the topic and how many words from the 25 available are the correct answer. I’ve yet to see this game fail to entertain a large group of people and if you wanted to play online during these quarantine times, a free digital implementation for this game is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://codenames.game/&quot;&gt;codenames.game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/225694/decrypto&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Decrypto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another word deduction game, from Thomas Dagenais-Lespérance, where teams try to guess a numerical code related to a sequence of known words while, at the same time, trying to deduce the opponent team’s words. It’s a great game of cunning and silly clues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/262543/wavelength&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wavelength&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a recent release from designers Alex Hague, Justin Vickers, and Wolfgang Warsch. This game is all about teams trying to gauge where a clue lies on a scale between two opposite concepts. It might seem strange but finding out how “eating” ranks on a scale from “non essential” to “essential” in your friend’s opinion is super fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/codenames.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Codenames, Vlaada Chvátil&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Codenames, Vlaada Chvátil&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-deduction-games&quot;&gt;Social deduction games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In social deduction games players are assigned a secret identity, tipically belonging to a faction, and try to achieve some goals while deducing the other player’s identities or allegiance. These games have become very popular thanks, especially, to games like &lt;em&gt;Werewolf&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mafia&lt;/em&gt;. These are essentially the same game (the name depends on regionality or preferences) and require nothing more than the group of players. There are, however, some modern games that I’d like to highlight for this caregory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/188834/secret-hitler&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secret Hitler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Mike Boxleiter, Tommy Maranges, and Max Temkin, sees players divided between fascists and liberals trying to pass laws for their own team while hiding their identity. Although nice, I find that this game suffers a bit too much from the luck of the draw, which makes for an interesting but very swingy experience. A digital implementation for this game is available for free on &lt;a href=&quot;https://tabletopia.com/games/secret-hitler&quot;&gt;Tabletopia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/128882/resistance-avalon&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Resistance: Avalon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from Don Eskridge reimplements &lt;em&gt;The Resistance&lt;/em&gt; and adds a few interesting elements. While playing in a pretty similar way to &lt;em&gt;Secret Hitler&lt;/em&gt; I feel that it removes some of the luck making it a more thinky and deductive game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/134352/two-rooms-and-boom&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two rooms and a boom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, designed by Alan Gerding and Sean McCoy, deviates from the previous games in that it creates a much bigger experience. This game is often played at conventions where a large group of people is divided in two teams and a variety of roles communicate and plot to have or not have the president and the bomb in the same room at the end of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;suggestion-games&quot;&gt;Suggestion games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though you might already be in the know when it comes to board games, you might be wondering what I mean by suggestion games. There’s a lot of games that came out in the last ten years or so that revolve around the mechanisms of providing a suggestion or definition with the purpose of conveying and information to other players. While some of the games I mentioned for the team game section above fulfill this definition, the games that I categorize here remove the team component and make the games all vs all or cooperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/39856/dixit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dixit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was designed by Jean-Louis Roubira and is one of my favourite games. It was, by far, the game most responsible of getting me deep into the hobby. The marvelous illustrations from Marie Cardouat (in the base set) and the ingenious rules led me to research artists, game awards, mechanics, expansions and go down the rabbit hole of board games. In &lt;em&gt;Dixit&lt;/em&gt;, one player per round provides a clue for one of the amazingly illustrated cards with the goal of letting someone, but not everyone, guess. The other players try to deceive the oppontents with cards that also fit the definition. In my experience, Dixit very rarely fails to amuse players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/147151/concept&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Concept&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Gaëtan Beaujannot and Alain Rivollet surprised me when I bought it without knowing much about it. If you know &lt;em&gt;Taboo&lt;/em&gt; you already know half of the rules. In &lt;em&gt;Concept&lt;/em&gt; though, you need to let somebody guess a word or phrase without talking. Instead you’ll use coloured cubes and exclamation points to describe the concepts that make up the answer. Describing “Die Hard” as a movie with terrorists that airs on Christmas might easily be interpreted as a movie about waging war on Santa Claus. While points don’t really matter, laughs are guaranteed. This game also has a very nice free digital implementation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamearena.com/gamepanel?game=concept&quot;&gt;Board Game Arena&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/254640/just-one&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just One&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from Ludovic Roudy and Bruno Sautter is the most recent of these games and definitely one that has had a lot of success in the past couple of years. Differently than the previous mentions, this is a cooperative games where all players give clues to a single guesser about a word. To do that, they write a single word but if two clues match they are deleted before the guesser can see them. The cooperative element is beautifully implemented here, as you try to think like the group in order not to write like the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/concept.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Concept, Gaëtan Beaujannot and Alain Rivollet&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Concept, Gaëtan Beaujannot and Alain Rivollet&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blurring-the-lines&quot;&gt;Blurring the lines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably noticed that this classification is not so precise and there’s some overlap even for the games I mentioned. The lines can get even more blurred as designers come up with new mechanisms and innovative ways of creating fun party games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/181304/mysterium&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mysterium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, was designed by Oleksandr Nevskiy and Oleg Sidorenko, and might make you think of &lt;em&gt;Dixit&lt;/em&gt;, in many ways. This is however a cooperative game were a player takes on the role of a ghost which tries to help the rest of the players, impersonating mediums, reconstruct their murder. This is done by providing beautifully illustrated cards in absolute silence in the hope that the mediums will be able to discuss and connect the dots on what this silent ghost is trying to convey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/252526/pictomania-second-edition&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pictomania (Second Edition)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another great game designed by Vlaada Chvátil that gives a new spin to drawing games like &lt;em&gt;Pictionary&lt;/em&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Pictomania&lt;/em&gt; players all draw and guess at the same time from a list of possible clues. Knowing that nobody else can have the same clue that you have, you are challenged in guessing other’s people drawing as fast as possible while still making one for your clue that is understandable. Even though this game plays up to 6 it’s a guaranteed laugh at a small party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/198454/when-i-dream&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I Dream&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from Chris Darsaklis, is another of those games that pleasantly surprised me when I bought it on a whim. As in many other examples before, in this game players give single word clues to a dreamer but each player might want them to guess correctly or incorrectly. It’s up to the guesser to decide whom to trust. But the best part of this game is probably the end of the round, when the dreamer can try to earn extra points by stringing together all guessed words in a dream. Watching people struggle to remember the last three words they said is exhilarating and, in its simplicity, an ingenious design choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/when-i-dream.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;When I Dream, Chris Darsaklis&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;When I Dream, Chris Darsaklis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fun-in-party-games&quot;&gt;The fun in party games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw what makes a party game and what are some notable example but why would you play one? Surely being at a party is already fun (even though the introvert in me would like to disagree), so why would I want to set rules to the experience? I think these games possess two aspects that make them perfect for social gatherings and even slightly separate them from other board games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Party games are extremely welcoming to new players. As I mentioned here and in previous posts, these games played a major part in drawing me to the hobby, as they don’t set an entry barrier. Most of the games that I mentioned can be played by literally anyone, regardless of age or experience. They create fun by mainly leveraging the players’ personalities and creativity, removing the complexities of learning game mechanics. This also means that they can be played by experienced and new players at the same time without impacting either’s enjoyment of the game itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And enjoying the game is actully the second strength of party games, as they put the focus on the experience itself. All games should be enjoyed regardless of the outcome but most of them rely on the players remaining in the &lt;em&gt;magic circle&lt;/em&gt; and abiding to the rules, the most important of which often is that one should play to win. Lots of board games break if players cease to try to win but the focus that party games put on the experience is such that elation is caused by the activity rather than the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So whether you are a a new player approaching the hobby or an experienced gamer, I recommend no to overlook party games: the creativity of grandma’s clue in &lt;em&gt;Dixit&lt;/em&gt; might just surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">Parties: 2020 hasn’t seen a lot of those. At the time I’m writing this post party is an almost obsolete word that mostly applies to looking at people’s heads through a screen. But social gatherings were, are and will be extremely important. So it shouldn’t come as a surprise that a very successful category of the board gaming hobby is represented by Party Games.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/dixit.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Point Salad: you gotta eat your greens!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Point Salad: you gotta eat your greens!" /><published>2020-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad.html">&lt;p&gt;Whatever the season, you should always eat your vegetables. Like a good rich salad, with lettuce, tomatoes, carrots. The problem is: I don’t like salad! Lucky for me, I do love me some &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/274960/point-salad&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is a 2 to 6 player card game all about points by Molly Johnson, Robert Melvin, and Shawn Stankewich. Its name comes from a popular expression in board games, used to indicate games where every thing you do scores you point. This is usually used with a negative meaning. &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; takes this notion and turns it on its head, making it the pillar of the game and building fun on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The box comes with a deck of 108 unique cards and a rulebook. Each card represents one of six vegetables on one side and a unique scoring rule on the other. Players take turn picking cards to use them either as vegetables or for their scoring conditions. That’s it, it’s as simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/point-salad.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Game setup for Point Salad&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Game setup for Point Salad&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But where does the fun come from?”, you might be asking. Well before I played this game I didn’t know stealing an onion from other people could be so entertaining. The tears on their eyes as if you just sliced it in front of their faces. See, &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is not just about building your collection of vegetables and scoring cards, it’s especially about preventing other players from doing the same. As in many drafting games, blocking opponents from accessing good cards is an integral part of the strategy and the great thing about this game is that &lt;em&gt;hate drafting&lt;/em&gt;, as this practice is often called, almost always scores you point as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of the cards is quite good, packaging is compact and portable, and the art is lovely. In its simplicity, the game looks very good on the table, with its vibrant colours and cartoony vibes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/point-salad-table.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This games looks good on the table however you put it&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;This games looks good on the table however you put it&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iconography for the scoring rules is super simple and self explanatory although some rules use plain text, which makes the game language dependent. This is easily overcome by explaining the card when it’s encountered, which will also clarify similar rules that apply to different vegetables. I played my Italian version with some English speaking friends and they had no trouble playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, I played a number of drafting games and, despite the fact that it’s not one of my favourite mechanisms (I must say I’m also usually rubbish at them), I think &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is a great introduction to the genre and to the hobby in general. The rules are super simple, everything is displayed on the table so no memory is required and the reward of every action is instantaneous. It feels great to take those two tomatoes that you were hoping for and it’s horrible to see that magnificent rule that matched your carrot collection get flipped and become inaccessible forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game brings a quick and exhilarating experience to the table that makes for a perfect filler but can easily become the main course as you find yourself playing over and over again. So, next time you’re wondering what to have for dinner, you can’t go wrong with a nice &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Whatever the season, you should always eat your vegetables. Like a good rich salad, with lettuce, tomatoes, carrots. The problem is: I don’t like salad! Lucky for me, I do love me some Point Salad!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/point-salad-detail.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Game Vocabulary: the first steps!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game Vocabulary: the first steps!" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary.html">&lt;p&gt;So you decided that you might actually be into board games and you want to know what to look for. As I said in my &lt;a href=&quot;/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, the best person who can tell what you’ll like to play is &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. But if you want to embark on the voyage to find your own true taste, first you need to learn how to sail. And even before that, you need to know the jargon (I have zero experience in sailing but I know sailors use some very peculiar words).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you start reading reviews, visiting BGG (which I introduced &lt;a href=&quot;/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), watching videos and listening to podcasts, you’ll start coming across many words which most times are given for granted by the speaker. This is one of the aspects of the hobby that pushed me to start this blog. I will post a number of entries dedicated to these words and the mechanics or game types they represent. But here I’d like to introduce you to four omnipresent terms that you might hear or read in the context of board games:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Euro&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;American-style&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filler&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract-games&quot;&gt;Abstract games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An abstract strategy game is a strategy game in which the theme is not important to the experience of playing” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_strategy_game&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;). These games usually have no luck involved, perfect information (i.e. nothing is hidden form other players) and resemble &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thegamesjournal.com/articles/DefiningtheAbstract.shtml&quot;&gt;a series of puzzles that the player pose to each other&lt;/a&gt;.  This means that most classic or ancient board games would fall in this category: think &lt;em&gt;Chess&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Go&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Checkers&lt;/em&gt;. Today there are however examples of games that do have non-deterministic elements, like dice or cards to be drawn, or hidden information but are still classified as abstract games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, when I read or hear someone defining a game as abstract, I assume that they mean a game in which the theme is very circumstantial and might be swapped with anything else without changing how the game feels. As we’ll see in the next paragraph, Euro games tend to overcome that by trying to intertwine (most times) the theme with the rules themselves. Few examples of modern abstract games are &lt;em&gt;Hive&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Santorini&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Onitama&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Blue Lagoon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/blue-lagoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blue Lagoon, Reiner Knizia&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Blue Lagoon, Reiner Knizia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;euro-games&quot;&gt;Euro Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term Euro game is probably the most outdated that I’ll be talking about today. Euro games are sometimes (rarely nowadays) called German-style games due to the country where they first were popularized in the 60’s. It was in the 90’s however, with the publication of &lt;em&gt;Settlers of Catan&lt;/em&gt;, that this kind of games became popular outside of Europe, awarding the category its name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euro game is often used as a catch-all term for games with indirect player interaction, no or few luck elements, and simple themes, loosely coupled with the rules. However, most games are often put under this category when they rely on one of the following mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tile Placement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auctions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trading and Negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set Collection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Area Control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worker Placement or Role Selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll get into the details of what each of these mean in future articles. For the moment it should suffice you to know that when somebody calls a game a Euro it’s often talking about a board game with abstract components (wooden cubes, meeples, card board tokens) and less conflict or thematic setting than an American-style game or a wargame.&lt;br /&gt;
A classic example of euro game is &lt;em&gt;Agricola&lt;/em&gt;. In this game, players are farmers that strive to grow crop, improve their homes and raise livestock better than their competitors. Although the theme could be considered dull and unrelatable by most players, the available actions resonate better with the theme than, for instance, the movements of kings and queens do in chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays games tend to have more interesting themes and value aesthetics highly, which is making the definition of Euro games more and more difficult. Moreover, some definitions actually decouple the theme from the rules, highlighting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Eurogame&quot;&gt;higher dependency on game mechanics&lt;/a&gt;. Other examples of modern Euro games are &lt;em&gt;Carcassonne&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Voyages of Marco Polo&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Modern Art&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/agricola.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Agricola, Uwe Rosenberg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Agricola, Uwe Rosenberg&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re into Podcasts, Ludology has a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://ludology.libsyn.com/gametek-classic-188-eurogames&quot;&gt;GameTek episode&lt;/a&gt; covering the origin and evolution of Euro games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-style-games&quot;&gt;American-style games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we wanted to make it easy to understand what a Euro game is, we could just say that it’s a board game that it’s neither abstract nor an American-style game. Amerigames originated, unsurprisingly, in the USA and feature direct interaction and conflict between the players, high thematic involvement and strong dependency on luck. An alternative term, often used for this kind of games, is &lt;em&gt;Ameritrash&lt;/em&gt;, which I have personally heard used almost always with a positive connotation.&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly to Euro games, the definition has grown looser over time and is usually used to contrast the former. Amerigames often features miniature figures (or minis) that might be painted (and that’s a whole hobby in itself). I personally have small experience with these types of games apart from classic examples like &lt;em&gt;Diplomacy&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Risk!&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my opinion, suffer the test of time and can be replaced with much more valid alternatives. Examples of modern Amerigames are &lt;em&gt;Battlestar Galactica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cosmic Encounter&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with their counterpart, Ludology also has a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://ludology.libsyn.com/gametek-classic-190-ameritrash&quot;&gt;episode on Ameritrash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small parenthesis is worth dedicating to wargames, games that simulate warfare realistically. These are among the oldest non-abstract board games and represent, from my experience, a niche inside the niche. I know very little about this genre so if you think you might be interested I suggest to start from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgamecategory/1019/wargame&quot;&gt;BoardGameGeek definition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;filler-games&quot;&gt;Filler games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the word filler is one you are bound to hear often and one that may be of great interest for new people getting into the hobby. Fillers are games that, during a board game night or event, are usually played between main games or at its beginning or end. This means that people usually categorize as fillers games that take up to 30 minutes, require very little or no setup on the table and have easy to explain rules. Most card games, for instance, are usually put under this category.&lt;br /&gt;
Once again, the definition is very loose and some would even consider 60 minutes games as fillers. Filler games that also have a high player count are also often called &lt;em&gt;party games&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started in the hobby, most of my collection was composed of fillers as I could only dedicate short periods of time to games or wanted to add variety to a game night. And honestly, I have found over the years a lot of fillers that are really fun and are able to fit a very interesting experience in small boxes and time windows. Few examples of some of my favorite filler games are &lt;em&gt;Arboretum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Biblios&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sushi Go&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Railroad Ink&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/sushi-go.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sushi Go, Phil Walker-Harding&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sushi Go, Phil Walker-Harding&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know some of the most popular terms used to quickly categorize games. If you’re like me, you’ll start from party games and then expand your collection to Euro games. But you might also immediately fall in love with the confrontation and thematic appeal of american-style games. Whatever it will be, you will know what people mean when they say they loved the filler that you just played.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">So you decided that you might actually be into board games and you want to know what to look for. As I said in my previous post, the best person who can tell what you’ll like to play is you. But if you want to embark on the voyage to find your own true taste, first you need to learn how to sail. And even before that, you need to know the jargon (I have zero experience in sailing but I know sailors use some very peculiar words).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/Queendomino-detail.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Board Game Geek: all you didn’t know you needed!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Board Game Geek: all you didn't know you needed!" /><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html">&lt;p&gt;Surely it would be great to have a central source of information about the board gaming hobby, apart from this awesome blog. After all, movies have &lt;em&gt;IMDB&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rotten Tomatoes&lt;/em&gt;, books have &lt;em&gt;GoodRead&lt;/em&gt; and pretty much any form of media has some kind of repository with juicy, useful information. Well, in board games you need to look no further than &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Board Game Geek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BGG was founded in 2000 by Scott Alden and Derk Solko and has been recognized during its many years of existence as “a resource without peer for board and card gamers, the recognized authority of this online community” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dianajonesaward.org/the-2010-award/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). There’s definitely a lot that can be explored about the platform, its branches, spin-offs, events, market, and forum. But what I’d like to focus on today’s post is one of the most useful features for somebody approaching the hobby for the first time: the &lt;em&gt;game pages&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-pages&quot;&gt;Game pages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to look at the details contained in such useful pages I will be using &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/140934/arboretum&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arboretum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favourite light games, as a reference.
The part that I usually peruse the most is also the first thing you’re going to notice about the game page: the banner. This packs a lot of useful information and makes them available at a glance. Here you’ll find things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cover art&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average rating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name of the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Year of release&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of players&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimated play time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Age reccomendation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and more. Some of these are self-explanatory but some are related to the way BGG works and perfectly represent why the site is such a good tool for the hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cool-info&quot;&gt;Cool info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average rating is based on a score assigned from users to the game, on a scale of &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Ratings&amp;amp;redirectedfrom=rating#&quot;&gt;1 to 10&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone can score the games so long as they have a registered BGG account. This score is used to rank all of the games in the database into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/browse/boardgame&quot;&gt;single huge list&lt;/a&gt; or each in its own category.&lt;br /&gt;
Now, as with any review-based platform, you should take the scores with a grain of salt as board games tastes are very personal. However, considering how many people usually rank each game, this number is a very good indicator of popularity albeit not always of accessibility. At the time of this post, the first game on BGG is &lt;em&gt;Gloomhaven&lt;/em&gt; which, although extremely loved by most people who played it, is a quite expensive and heavy game. So when you’re deciding which game to buy next, don’t rely too much on the score: some of the games I love the most, like &lt;em&gt;Heul Doch Mau Mau&lt;/em&gt;, are in the 6.5 region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/Arboretum.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Arboretum, Dan Cassar&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Arboretum, Dan Cassar&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of players is another useful piece of information that you will find in the page. Here are shown not only minimum and maximum number of players but also the best value based, as always, on user reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the one, non-trivial value you will find in the banner is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Weight&quot;&gt;weight&lt;/a&gt;. This is a 1 to 5 number that represents how difficult a game is to understand. The weigth is, usually, what people refer to when they talk of light, medium or heavy games but, as with the score, its perceived value will differ from person to person and change with time and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you move past the banner you will find an overview of the game, pictures of game components and boards, rundowns of the rules, awards, overviews, and a plethora of useful information.&lt;br /&gt;
The overview contains the classification of the game which shows information such as &lt;em&gt;Type&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Category&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mechanisms&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I will cover in future posts. But if you really want to dig into the site and discover great things for yourself, I suggest starting from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Guide_To_BoardGameGeek&quot;&gt;BGG guide&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/glossary&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, next time you see a game and you’re wondering what people think of it, take a look on BGG and if you ever have a question about a rule or a component in a new game, don’t forget to look in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/forums/region/1/bgg&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt;, somebody probably already asked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">Surely it would be great to have a central source of information about the board gaming hobby, apart from this awesome blog. After all, movies have IMDB and Rotten Tomatoes, books have GoodRead and pretty much any form of media has some kind of repository with juicy, useful information. Well, in board games you need to look no further than Board Game Geek.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/Arboretum-cards.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to ABG!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to ABG!" /><published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html">&lt;p&gt;So you’ve been to a friend’s house party and you had a blast playing a game where everyone was laughing and cheering. Or maybe it was a rainy day and you decided to dust off your copy of an old game you hadn’t play since your childhood and ended up having the best time with the whole family. It could even be that a person you just met showed you a surprising card game that you didn’t know existed and you ended up playing for the whole afternoon while getting to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it was, something probably happened that made you wonder one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is a board game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are board games up to nowadays?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there something else like what I just played?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s the case you might be discovering an interest in boardgames and you probably want some answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-board-game&quot;&gt;What is a board game?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tabletop games are games that are normally played on a table or other flat surface, such as board games, card games, dice games, miniature wargames or tile-based games.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabletop_game&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that sounds generic…and in fairness, it is! I tend to use the term board game instead of tabletop game and you will find that a lot of other people do too. Moreover, I would categorize as board games even games that don’t require being played on a table or don’t have a game board (for instance, a lot of party games).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, a board game is an experience with defined rules, a limited duration (at times a very long one) and that usually comes in a box. But you probably already knew that, didn’t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG/assets/img/ttr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ticket To Ride Europe, Alan R. Moon&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ticket To Ride Europe, Alan R. Moon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-board-games-up-to-nowadays&quot;&gt;What are board games up to nowadays?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably played some board game at some point or another in your life. &lt;em&gt;Monopoly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Clue&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Risiko&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt;, they all count. Even your regional card game could be considered a tabletop game.&lt;br /&gt;
Today, however, board gaming is an interestingly vast hobby with over 4000 new games being released every year (see for instance &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/search/boardgame/page/1?advsearch=1&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;include%5Bdesignerid%5D=&amp;amp;include%5Bpublisherid%5D=&amp;amp;geekitemname=&amp;amp;range%5Byearpublished%5D%5Bmin%5D=2019&amp;amp;range%5Byearpublished%5D%5Bmax%5D=2019&amp;amp;range%5Bminage%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bnumvoters%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bnumweights%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bminplayers%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bmaxplayers%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bleastplaytime%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bplaytime%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgrating%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgrating%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgweight%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgweight%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;colfiltertype=&amp;amp;searchuser=&amp;amp;nosubtypes%5B0%5D=boardgameexpansion&amp;amp;playerrangetype=normal&amp;amp;B1=Submit&quot;&gt;games published in 2019&lt;/a&gt;). This might seem a lot to get into for a new hobby but don’t worry, there are some good resources out there to help you start looking around (who knows, maybe this blog is one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-there-something-else-like-what-i-just-played&quot;&gt;Is there something else like what I just played?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you just played &lt;em&gt;Carcassonne&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Catan&lt;/em&gt; for the first time and you found it interesting. Now you would like to try something similar but with a little more pizazz. You open an online store, you type the name of the game you just played, start looking for related products, and you immediately get overwhelmed by a million games with different themes, art, rules, reviews, ratings. Perhaps you even start buying some (I know I did).&lt;br /&gt;
But wait, do you even know what you want from your games? Experience will definitely shape your tastes but why not going into it with somewhat of an idea already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what this blog would like to be: an unqualified primer to the marvelous world of board games. It’s what I would’ve liked to have had when first going into the hobby. Here I will post about game vocabulary, game types, resources, and everything you need to find out what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; really like.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">So you’ve been to a friend’s house party and you had a blast playing a game where everyone was laughing and cheering. Or maybe it was a rainy day and you decided to dust off your copy of an old game you hadn’t play since your childhood and ended up having the best time with the whole family. It could even be that a person you just met showed you a surprising card game that you didn’t know existed and you ended up playing for the whole afternoon while getting to know each other.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/ABG-team.jpeg" /></entry></feed>