<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2020-12-07T11:25:37+01:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ahead of the Board Game</title><subtitle>The fun of getting into board games</subtitle><author><name>4binary1</name></author><entry><title type="html">Point Salad - You gotta eat your greens</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Point Salad - You gotta eat your greens" /><published>2020-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/review/Point-Salad.html">&lt;p&gt;Whatever the season, you should always eat your vegetables. Like a good rich salad, with lettuce, tomatoes, carrots. The problem is: I don’t like salad! Lucky for me, I do love me some &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/274960/point-salad&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is a 2 to 6 player card game all about points by Molly Johnson, Robert Melvin, and Shawn Stankewich. Its name comes from a popular expression in board games, used to indicate games where every thing you do scores you point. This is usually used with a negative meaning. &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; takes this notion and turns it on its head, making it the pillar of the game and building fun on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The box comes with a deck of 108 unique cards and a rulebook. Each card represents one of six vegetables on one side and a unique scoring rule on the other. Players take turn picking cards to use them either as vegetables or for their scoring conditions. That’s it, it’s as simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/point-salad.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Game setup for _Point Salad_&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Game setup for _Point Salad_&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But where does the fun come from?”, you might be asking. Well before I played this game I didn’t know stealing an onion from other people could be so entertaining. The tears on their eyes as if you just sliced it in front of their faces. See, &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is not just about building your collection of vegetables and scoring cards, it’s especially about preventing other players from doing the same. As in many drafting games, blocking opponents from accessing good cards is an integral part of the strategy and the great thing about this game is that &lt;em&gt;hate drafting&lt;/em&gt;, as this practice is often called, almost always scores you point as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of the cards is quite good, packaging is compact and portable, and the art is lovely. In its simplicity, the game looks very good on the table, with its vibrant colours and cartoony vibes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/point-salad-table.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;This games looks good on the table however you put it&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;This games looks good on the table however you put it&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iconography for the scoring rules is super simple and self explanatory although some rules use plain text, which makes the game language dependent. This is easily overcome by explaining the card when it’s encountered, which will also clarify similar rules that apply to different vegetables. I played my Italian version with some English speaking friends and they had no trouble playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, I played a number of drafting games and, despite the fact that it’s not one of my favourite mechanisms (I must say I’m also usually rubbish at them), I think &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt; is a great introduction to the genre and to the hobby in general. The rules are super simple, everything is displayed on the table so no memory is required and the reward of every action is instantaneous. It feels great to take those two tomatoes that you were hoping for and it’s horrible to see that magnificent rule that matched your carrot collection get flipped and become inaccessible forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game brings a quick and exhilarating experience to the table that makes for a perfect filler but can easily become the main course as you find yourself playing over and over again. So, next time you’re wondering what to have for dinner, you can’t go wrong with a nice &lt;em&gt;Point Salad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Whatever the season, you should always eat your vegetables. Like a good rich salad, with lettuce, tomatoes, carrots. The problem is: I don’t like salad! Lucky for me, I do love me some Point Salad!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/point-salad-detail.jpeg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Game Vocabulary - The first steps!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game Vocabulary - The first steps!" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Game-Vocabulary.html">&lt;p&gt;So you decided that you might actually be into board games and you want to know what to look for. As I said in my &lt;a href=&quot;/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, the best person who can tell what you’ll like to play is &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. But if you want to embark on the voyage to find your own true taste, first you need to learn how to sail. And even before that, you need to know the jargon (I have zero experience in sailing but I know sailors use some very peculiar words).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you start reading reviews, visiting BGG (which I introduced &lt;a href=&quot;/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), watching videos and listening to podcasts, you’ll start coming across many words which most times are given for granted by the speaker. This is one of the aspects of the hobby that pushed me to start this blog. I will post a number of entries dedicated to these words and the mechanics or game types they represent. But here I’d like to introduce you to four omnipresent terms that you might hear or read in the context of board games:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Euro&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;American-style&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filler&lt;/strong&gt; games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract-games&quot;&gt;Abstract games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An abstract strategy game is a strategy game in which the theme is not important to the experience of playing” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_strategy_game&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;). These games usually have no luck involved, perfect information (i.e. nothing is hidden form other players) and resemble &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thegamesjournal.com/articles/DefiningtheAbstract.shtml&quot;&gt;a series of puzzles that the player pose to each other&lt;/a&gt;.  This means that most classic or ancient board games would fall in this category: think &lt;em&gt;Chess&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Go&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Checkers&lt;/em&gt;. Today there are however examples of games that do have non-deterministic elements, like dice or cards to be drawn, or hidden information but are still classified as abstract games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, when I read or hear someone defining a game as abstract, I assume that they mean a game in which the theme is very circumstantial and might be swapped with anything else without changing how the game feels. As we’ll see in the next paragraph, Euro games tend to overcome that by trying to intertwine (most times) the theme with the rules themselves. Few examples of modern abstract games are &lt;em&gt;Hive&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Santorini&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Onitama&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Blue Lagoon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/blue-lagoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blue Lagoon, Reiner Knizia&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Blue Lagoon, Reiner Knizia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;euro-games&quot;&gt;Euro Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term Euro game is probably the most outdated that I’ll be talking about today. Euro games are sometimes (rarely nowadays) called German-style games due to the country where they first were popularized in the 60’s. It was in the 90’s however, with the publication of &lt;em&gt;Settlers of Catan&lt;/em&gt;, that this kind of games became popular outside of Europe, awarding the category its name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euro game is often used as a catch-all term for games with indirect player interaction, no or few luck elements, and simple themes, loosely coupled with the rules. However, most games are often put under this category when they rely on one of the following mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tile Placement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auctions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trading and Negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set Collection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Area Control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worker Placement or Role Selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll get into the details of what each of these mean in future articles. For the moment it should suffice you to know that when somebody calls a game a Euro it’s often talking about a board game with abstract components (wooden cubes, meeples, card board tokens) and less conflict or thematic setting than an American-style game or a wargame.&lt;br /&gt;
A classic example of euro game is &lt;em&gt;Agricola&lt;/em&gt;. In this game, players are farmers that strive to grow crop, improve their homes and raise livestock better than their competitors. Although the theme could be considered dull and unrelatable by most players, the available actions resonate better with the theme than, for instance, the movements of kings and queens do in chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays games tend to have more interesting themes and value aesthetics highly, which is making the definition of Euro games more and more difficult. Moreover, some definitions actually decouple the theme from the rules, highlighting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Eurogame&quot;&gt;higher dependency on game mechanics&lt;/a&gt;. Other examples of modern Euro games are &lt;em&gt;Carcassonne&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Voyages of Marco Polo&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Modern Art&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/agricola.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Agricola, Uwe Rosenberg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Agricola, Uwe Rosenberg&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re into Podcasts, Ludology has a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://ludology.libsyn.com/gametek-classic-188-eurogames&quot;&gt;GameTek episode&lt;/a&gt; covering the origin and evolution of Euro games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-style-games&quot;&gt;American-style games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we wanted to make it easy to understand what a Euro game is, we could just say that it’s a board game that it’s neither abstract nor an American-style game. Amerigames originated, unsurprisingly, in the USA and feature direct interaction and conflict between the players, high thematic involvement and strong dependency on luck. An alternative term, often used for this kind of games, is &lt;em&gt;Ameritrash&lt;/em&gt;, which I have personally heard used almost always with a positive connotation.&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly to Euro games, the definition has grown looser over time and is usually used to contrast the former. Amerigames often features miniature figures (or minis) that might be painted (and that’s a whole hobby in itself). I personally have small experience with these types of games apart from classic examples like &lt;em&gt;Diplomacy&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Risk!&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my opinion, suffer the test of time and can be replaced with much more valid alternatives. Examples of modern Amerigames are &lt;em&gt;Battlestar Galactica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cosmic Encounter&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with their counterpart, Ludology also has a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://ludology.libsyn.com/gametek-classic-190-ameritrash&quot;&gt;episode on Ameritrash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small parenthesis is worth dedicating to wargames, games that simulate warfare realistically. These are among the oldest non-abstract board games and represent, from my experience, a niche inside the niche. I know very little about this genre so if you think you might be interested I suggest to start from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgamecategory/1019/wargame&quot;&gt;BoardGameGeek definition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;filler-games&quot;&gt;Filler games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the word filler is one you are bound to hear often and one that may be of great interest for new people getting into the hobby. Fillers are games that, during a board game night or event, are usually played between main games or at its beginning or end. This means that people usually categorize as fillers games that take up to 30 minutes, require very little or no setup on the table and have easy to explain rules. Most card games, for instance, are usually put under this category.&lt;br /&gt;
Once again, the definition is very loose and some would even consider 60 minutes games as fillers. Filler games that also have a high player count are also often called &lt;em&gt;party games&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started in the hobby, most of my collection was composed of fillers as I could only dedicate short periods of time to games or wanted to add variety to a game night. And honestly, I have found over the years a lot of fillers that are really fun and are able to fit a very interesting experience in small boxes and time windows. Few examples of some of my favorite filler games are &lt;em&gt;Arboretum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Biblios&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sushi Go&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Railroad Ink&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/sushi-go.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sushi Go, Phil Walker-Harding&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sushi Go, Phil Walker-Harding&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know some of the most popular terms used to quickly categorize games. If you’re like me, you’ll start from party games and then expand your collection to Euro games. But you might also immediately fall in love with the confrontation and thematic appeal of american-style games. Whatever it will be, you will know what people mean when they say they loved the filler that you just played.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">So you decided that you might actually be into board games and you want to know what to look for. As I said in my previous post, the best person who can tell what you’ll like to play is you. But if you want to embark on the voyage to find your own true taste, first you need to learn how to sail. And even before that, you need to know the jargon (I have zero experience in sailing but I know sailors use some very peculiar words).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/Queendomino-detail.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Board Game Geek - All you didn’t know you needed!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Board Game Geek - All you didn't know you needed!" /><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Board-Game-Geek.html">&lt;p&gt;Surely it would be great to have a central source of information about the board gaming hobby, apart from this awesome blog. After all, movies have &lt;em&gt;IMDB&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rotten Tomatoes&lt;/em&gt;, books have &lt;em&gt;GoodRead&lt;/em&gt; and pretty much any form of media has some kind of repository with juicy, useful information. Well, in board games you need to look no further than &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Board Game Geek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BGG was founded in 2000 by Scott Alden and Derk Solko and has been recognized during its many years of existence as “a resource without peer for board and card gamers, the recognized authority of this online community” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dianajonesaward.org/the-2010-award/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). There’s definitely a lot that can be explored about the platform, its branches, spin-offs, events, market, and forum. But what I’d like to focus on today’s post is one of the most useful features for somebody approaching the hobby for the first time: the &lt;em&gt;game pages&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-pages&quot;&gt;Game pages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to look at the details contained in such useful pages I will be using &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/140934/arboretum&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arboretum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favourite light games, as a reference.
The part that I usually peruse the most is also the first thing you’re going to notice about the game page: the banner. This packs a lot of useful information and makes them available at a glance. Here you’ll find things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cover art&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average rating&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name of the game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Year of release&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of players&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimated play time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Age reccomendation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Artists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and more. Some of these are self-explanatory but some are related to the way BGG works and perfectly represent why the site is such a good tool for the hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cool-info&quot;&gt;Cool info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average rating is based on a score assigned from users to the game, on a scale of &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Ratings&amp;amp;redirectedfrom=rating#&quot;&gt;1 to 10&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone can score the games so long as they have a registered BGG account. This score is used to rank all of the games in the database into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/browse/boardgame&quot;&gt;single huge list&lt;/a&gt; or each in its own category.&lt;br /&gt;
Now, as with any review-based platform, you should take the scores with a grain of salt as board games tastes are very personal. However, considering how many people usually rank each game, this number is a very good indicator of popularity albeit not always of accessibility. At the time of this post, the first game on BGG is &lt;em&gt;Gloomhaven&lt;/em&gt; which, although extremely loved by most people who played it, is a quite expensive and heavy game. So when you’re deciding which game to buy next, don’t rely too much on the score: some of the games I love the most, like &lt;em&gt;Heul Doch Mau Mau&lt;/em&gt;, are in the 6.5 region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/Arboretum.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Arboretum, Dan Cassar&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Arboretum, Dan Cassar&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of players is another useful piece of information that you will find in the page. Here are shown not only minimum and maximum number of players but also the best value based, as always, on user reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the one, non-trivial value you will find in the banner is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Weight&quot;&gt;weight&lt;/a&gt;. This is a 1 to 5 number that represents how difficult a game is to understand. The weigth is, usually, what people refer to when they talk of light, medium or heavy games but, as with the score, its perceived value will differ from person to person and change with time and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you move past the banner you will find an overview of the game, pictures of game components and boards, rundowns of the rules, awards, overviews, and a plethora of useful information.&lt;br /&gt;
The overview contains the classification of the game which shows information such as &lt;em&gt;Type&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Category&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mechanisms&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I will cover in future posts. But if you really want to dig into the site and discover great things for yourself, I suggest starting from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/Guide_To_BoardGameGeek&quot;&gt;BGG guide&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/glossary&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, next time you see a game and you’re wondering what people think of it, take a look on BGG and if you ever have a question about a rule or a component in a new game, don’t forget to look in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/forums/region/1/bgg&quot;&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt;, somebody probably already asked.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">Surely it would be great to have a central source of information about the board gaming hobby, apart from this awesome blog. After all, movies have IMDB and Rotten Tomatoes, books have GoodRead and pretty much any form of media has some kind of repository with juicy, useful information. Well, in board games you need to look no further than Board Game Geek.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/Arboretum-cards.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to ABG!</title><link href="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to ABG!" /><published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/primer/Welcome-to-ABG.html">&lt;p&gt;So you’ve been to a friend’s house party and you had a blast playing a game where everyone was laughing and cheering. Or maybe it was a rainy day and you decided to dust off your copy of an old game you hadn’t play since your childhood and ended up having the best time with the whole family. It could even be that a person you just met showed you a surprising card game that you didn’t know existed and you ended up playing for the whole afternoon while getting to know each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it was, something probably happened that made you wonder one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is a board game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are board games up to nowadays?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there something else like what I just played?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s the case you might be discovering an interest in boardgames and you probably want some answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-board-game&quot;&gt;What is a board game?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tabletop games are games that are normally played on a table or other flat surface, such as board games, card games, dice games, miniature wargames or tile-based games.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabletop_game&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that sounds generic…and in fairness, it is! I tend to use the term board game instead of tabletop game and you will find that a lot of other people do too. Moreover, I would categorize as board games even games that don’t require being played on a table or don’t have a game board (for instance, a lot of party games).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, a board game is an experience with defined rules, a limited duration (at times a very long one) and that usually comes in a box. But you probably already knew that, didn’t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;featured-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/ABG//assets/img/ttr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ticket To Ride Europe, Alan R. Moon&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ticket To Ride Europe, Alan R. Moon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-board-games-up-to-nowadays&quot;&gt;What are board games up to nowadays?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably played some board game at some point or another in your life. &lt;em&gt;Monopoly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Clue&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Risiko&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt;, they all count. Even your regional card game could be considered a tabletop game.&lt;br /&gt;
Today, however, board gaming is an interestingly vast hobby with over 4000 new games being released every year (see for instance &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/search/boardgame/page/1?advsearch=1&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;include%5Bdesignerid%5D=&amp;amp;include%5Bpublisherid%5D=&amp;amp;geekitemname=&amp;amp;range%5Byearpublished%5D%5Bmin%5D=2019&amp;amp;range%5Byearpublished%5D%5Bmax%5D=2019&amp;amp;range%5Bminage%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bnumvoters%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bnumweights%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bminplayers%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bmaxplayers%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bleastplaytime%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;range%5Bplaytime%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgrating%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgrating%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgweight%5D%5Bmin%5D=&amp;amp;floatrange%5Bavgweight%5D%5Bmax%5D=&amp;amp;colfiltertype=&amp;amp;searchuser=&amp;amp;nosubtypes%5B0%5D=boardgameexpansion&amp;amp;playerrangetype=normal&amp;amp;B1=Submit&quot;&gt;games published in 2019&lt;/a&gt;). This might seem a lot to get into for a new hobby but don’t worry, there are some good resources out there to help you start looking around (who knows, maybe this blog is one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-there-something-else-like-what-i-just-played&quot;&gt;Is there something else like what I just played?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you just played &lt;em&gt;Carcassonne&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Catan&lt;/em&gt; for the first time and you found it interesting. Now you would like to try something similar but with a little more pizazz. You open an online store, you type the name of the game you just played, start looking for related products, and you immediately get overwhelmed by a million games with different themes, art, rules, reviews, ratings. Perhaps you even start buying some (I know I did).&lt;br /&gt;
But wait, do you even know what you want from your games? Experience will definitely shape your tastes but why not going into it with somewhat of an idea already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what this blog would like to be: an unqualified primer to the marvelous world of board games. It’s what I would’ve liked to have had when first going into the hobby. Here I will post about game vocabulary, game types, resources, and everything you need to find out what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; really like.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>4binary1</name></author><category term="primer" /><summary type="html">So you’ve been to a friend’s house party and you had a blast playing a game where everyone was laughing and cheering. Or maybe it was a rainy day and you decided to dust off your copy of an old game you hadn’t play since your childhood and ended up having the best time with the whole family. It could even be that a person you just met showed you a surprising card game that you didn’t know existed and you ended up playing for the whole afternoon while getting to know each other.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://4binary1.github.io/ABG/ABG-team.jpeg" /></entry></feed>